Welcome to business central lunch
edition and our session about
withholding taxes in expense agent. So
before we start I first want to explain
what is about what is exactly
withholding tax and how we can use this
in expense uh agent expense management
related to employees. In general
withholding tax is tax deducted from a
so source from vendor or employee
payments. Um in a case of vendor in some
situation you need to deduct some taxes
when you pay vendors but for employees
maybe this is much more common because
in some situations you cannot receive
any money from your uh employees. You
need to pay some taxations to your
government. So if you are paid more than
is uh above some limit you need to pay
taxes on top of that. So this is what is
about and um in general companies remit
to tax authorities on pay's behalf and
it can go really complicated. We can use
different models uh different
calculation justification threshold so
on so on. So I will try to explain much
more into details but why it is there
why it matters because it assure
compliance with all local taxes laws. So
this is uh there is a small chance that
there is any um country
not required to pay taxes on some
payments for employees uh above some
limits because for some smaller amounts
of course maybe you do not need to pay
some situation but above some limits you
are definitely supposed to pay taxes. So
it reduce definitely uh risk of
penalties it uh improve um automation
posting compliance and so on. So what is
exactly in a business central related to
employees and the first place you will
see withholding uh tax posting setup.
This is existing tax posting setup
because we already had this earlier for
um vendors from previous wave. Now we
extended bit holding tax to employees as
well. So you will see we have now a few
uh fields with additional setup uh to
make this more compliance with the
employee related topics. So I will show
this in a demo much more details just to
emphasize. So this this is the same
process and any any other taxation this
is the same as VAT or with general
business posting groups. So you have um
withholding posting uh business posting
group and withholding product posting
group withholding business posting group
need to be assigned to employee card and
withholding product posting group need
to be assigned to category uh card. So
this is what you need to do. And then
when we have this uh extended how to use
um what is important to to remember that
you can have single uh product posting
group uh per category but you can have
even more complicated you can have
multiple uh product posting group per uh
category. Why is that? Because in some
situations and most of situations I
really hope you need to pay only one tax
uh per uh payment but in some situations
you are supposed to pay multiple two or
three for example state federal tax for
some payments. So you are able to
configure multiple posting business
posting groups per category in this case
but this is uh up to you. So you need to
make a setup based on your local
authorities rules. So what else? As you
have automatically uh calculation, we
need to have again some specific
situation how to set up. So you can
support both gross or net calculation.
It depends what you want because some
situation you want to pay thousand
dollars for some uh allowance and you
need to pay um taxes from this amount.
So this is a gross but in some situation
you want to pay your employee $1,000 and
you will pay taxes on a top of that. So
you can choose both of these options and
then if you have multiple um taxes uh
for one uh record as I mentioned because
you have multiple product posting groups
you can choose simple or compound uh
calculation and then we have uh
configurable thresholds uh uh per record
per period per category per period. So
you can see I will show in a demo again
much more in um in these details. So
let's go uh deep dive into the demo. I
will first start showing example and
then I will explain setup behind the
scene.
So now I am in expense agent my web app
and I want to create my mileage expense.
Why I'm using mileage? because I have in
a setup that I need to pay taxations if
my mileage payment is above $1,000.
So to make this I will imagine that I'm
traveling from Microsoft link [snorts]
and I will choose to make good trip from
Cophagen to Paris.
So that's a big trip and I can choose I
have route one 700 and something miles
another 800. So I will keep this shorter
only 772 kilome miles sorry and then if
I choose by car
I will see that I need to pay 1,000 and
if I choose same day round trip probably
nobody will do uh something similar but
let's imagine so I have $2,27
uh dollars to be paid. So what I need to
do I just want to create this expense.
Okay. Now I have created you can see
$2,000 a little bit more. I can review
and I can submit for approval. Reimburse
amount 2,000 by cash. So all good. And
that's fine. I submitted. I can see that
I submitted here. So this is expense
report 21. So now I will go back to
Business Central. Let's look into
expense reports.
I need to find this expense report. Yes,
this is the last one.
And I can see okay trip Microsoft to
Hayatt Regency all good the same amounts
everything is fine. So now if I look
into preview posting
you will see okay I have GL entry
employee ledger entry detail employee
ledger entry but I have vit holding tax
entry. So how I got this withholding tax
entries? If I open this entry, you will
see that I have okay posting date. This
is what I used basing the purchase
invoice. So I have base 2,127
and I have amount 425.40.
So you can see that this is actually
20%, I will show in the setup how it
look like. So this is normal withholding
tax user ID all these details are here
transaction number so I can go deeper
deeper to explain u based in a local
currency amount local currency you can
see that withholding tax is 20%. So
everything is there in entries. So
original document number so on so on. So
I will not go deeper into all these um
entries. I want to go back to show how I
have a setup.
So if I look into withholding posting
setup, you will see I will go to edit
list that I have withholding tax posting
business posting group expenses and I
have withholding tax [snorts] product
posting group mileage and then I have
withholding threshold type 1,000. So
everything above uh 1,000 will be
taxable withholding tax in 20%. So now I
can choose when to be calculated based
on invoice. So this is a moment when I
post expense report. So if I want to be
calculated in this moment I will choose
invoice. If I want to be calculated when
I'm paid as a employee in this case I
can choose payments. So it will be
unrealized until I'm paid. So then I
have my uh accounts I want to be posted
so on. What is important more this is
here on the end calculation base. You
can choose as I mentioned gross. In this
case it was a gross but you can choose
net or gross up. So you can choose
another way again simple if you have
only one this is always simple. If you
have multiple then you can choose simple
method to calculate it or compound for
calculation. We have documentation about
this functionality. So please go there
to understand how system calculates both
simple and compound models. And then
this one is probably much more important
because now
looking for employee perspective it can
be completely different how we uh in
which moment we became liable for taxes.
So it can be per record or line. So for
each transaction system will calculate
if you above threshold or not. In some
situation it can be okay it fits but not
always. In some other situation it can
be per document but much more in
especially related to employees uh
withholdings this is category per period
or total imperial. So this is much more
often again I cannot say for all
authorities and all countries it depends
from country to country from rules to
rules but you have a lot of options to
choose how you want to set up but in
this case I used for category in period
so for mileage for period but you can
use again total in period. So it depends
how you want to use if you choose in
period you need to choose which period
you want to track. So I use month but
you can see you have quarter year and
fiscal period. So whatever you want to
choose but again I said I want for
category period period is uh month as as
I choose uh uh category I need to set
which one category is applied. So I
choose mileage. What else I need to have
set up on employee card?
You can find
that I have withholding tax uh business
posting group. I have dedicated uh
posting group. I can say that this
person is exempt for taxation again. So
this this is possible to be done. And
then additional again it depends from
country to country. If you if you need
some certificates, Bitcoin tax
certificate number, Bitcoin certificate
type. So you can do if you need it. This
is not mandatory. And um let's make a
look into expense category
because I use mileage
and then you can see here I have
withholding tax posting uh withholding
tax group as I use single. You can see
you have single or tax group. If this is
single, I have mileage. This is what I
choose. But if you decide to use group
tax group in this case, you need to
define here vholding group code. And in
vit holding group code, you need to
create for example for mileage and then
you can add multiple uh business posting
groups um uh sorry a product posting
group related to this uh uh tax group
card because if you have federal, state
and the local tax or some insurance you
need to pay. This is a place where you
can configure and then you can set up uh
component order how system will
calculate one by one. So this is what
you need to set up to get this result.
So this is every everything about using
withholding for uh expenses management.
It can be used outside expense
management but we will have separate
session about finance. So you can see
much more about withholding tax for
employees there. So that's it. Thank you
for watching this video.